Amphibians are ancient creatures,
living fossils in a modern world.
But frogs, toads and salamanders
are more diverse,
colourful and creative
than you could ever imagine.
Whether dodging danger,
fighting rivals,
raising their young
or wearing a disguise,
amphibians are awesome.
So hop along to your local pond,
dive in
and explore the fascinating world
of the frogs and their cousins.
Dark, steaming, ancient forest.
Like a land that time forgot.
A monster
lurking beneath the surface.
It evolved in the Jurassic period.
This human-sized beast could have
been dodging the feet of dinosaurs.
But this is today.
A giant salamander.
It can hunt in darkness
by sensing prey.
It can breathe
through its skin underwater.
It can regrow limbs,
produce toxic slime
and live for nearly a century.
It's the crowning glory
of the amphibian family.
At school, every child is taught
that amphibians bridge the gap
between fish and reptiles.
Fish must live in water,
breed in water
and breathe oxygen from the water
through their gills.
Reptiles have adapted
to life on land.
They have scaly skin,
breathe with lungs
and most lay shelled eggs,
always on land.
Amphibians are totally unique.
Their name means 'both lives'.
They have mastered land and water.
They bridge both worlds
and can breathe air with lungs
or oxygen from water
through their skin.
But unlike reptiles,
they must lay their eggs in water
as they don't have hard shells
and could dry out.
Egg laying is quite a palaver ...
and all that most of us
see of our slimy neighbours.
Spring is in the air.
And the forest is buzzing.
There's a party,
and everyone's invited.
When European moor frogs are ready
to mate, they make quite a splash.
They're a locally abundant species.
Several hundred can rub shoulders
in every hectare of wetland.
But now they cram more in
from far and wide.
Up to 20 per square metre,
in a giant amphibian orgy.
The usually grey-brown males
flush ghostly blue in excitement.
They're looking
for available females
and don't intend to let one slip
through their fingers.
Their thumbs have nuptial pads,
rough areas, to give them a better
grip on their slippery lovers.
When a female is spotted,
the contest begins.
The male's endless chirping
and splashing draws an audience.
Master of stealth, the bittern is
a well-camouflaged heron.
Patience is his middle-name.
It's a waiting game
that usually pays off.
Ever heard the expression
'frog in the throat'?
Turns out wriggling frog
isn't the easiest thing to swallow.
It doesn't spoil
the party atmosphere though.
A successful male won't let go,
despite the best attempts of others
to dislodge him.
He needs to be in position
as the female releases her eggs.
In perfect synchrony, he pumps out
sperm over the mounds of jelly.
Each female can release anywhere
from a whopping 500 eggs
to an eye-watering three thousand!
The eggs are small but expand,
absorbing water to become the more
familiar mounds of frog spawn.
The sheer numbers seem excessive,
but the amphibian world
is constantly under attack.
This time a grey heron
invites itself to the party.
Frogs need large litters
to keep the population topped up.
So they keep at it.
They only breed for 20 days
or so each spring
and must make the most
of the narrow window.
All of their energy
goes into the next generation.
Then an amphibian miracle.
Each perfect globe undergoes
an incredible transformation.
The tiny larvae
wriggle free of their jelly mould.
There's not much
family resemblance.
Unlike the adults,
they extract oxygen from the water
through fingery gills.
They munch only
on microscopic algae.
But there's amphibian magic
on its way.
Over a few short weeks they undergo
a spectacular metamorphosis.
They start adding
tiny water creatures like daphnia,
the water flea, to their diet.
These minute crustaceans
are the basis of the food chain,
and are even eaten
by the plants themselves,
such as the carnivorous
utricularia!
The pond
offers a buffet of mini-meals.
As adult frogs
they won't eat plants at all.
Their life of carnivory
starts here.
Eventually
they'll absorb their own tails,
recycling the nutrients
into characteristic hoping legs.
The tadpole stage
lasts less than a month,
but it will be several years
until the frogs are big enough
to return for an orgy of their own.
The amphibians, frogs, toads and
salamanders, are pretty amazing.
And they've got
a long track record of success.
The first amphibians
crawled from primal swamps
around 370 million years ago.
At that time, sea levels
were falling, exposing new land.
Some fish,
similar to modern lungfish,
were experimenting with leg-like
fins and the first proto-type lungs
so that they could explore
the shores.
If a dry season
took away their pools,
they could survive
for short periods on land,
and even 'walk' to find water.
They were the first vertebrates
to ever venture above the surface.
A fashion that soon caught on.
It was the start of something big.
In these great-grandfathers
of amphibians,
fins gradually became fully
functional legs
that could support the body,
and gills disappeared altogether,
replaced by bigger
and more efficient lungs.
What was one small step for a fish,
was a giant leap
for amphibian kind.
It opened up a whole new world.
At that time, the only animals
were invertebrates.
A bug buffet.
and the amphibians
were the first to the feast.
In a humid, lush rainforest
landscape they thrived.
But the climate was changing,
drying.
They were left behind
when reptiles, and later, mammals,
started to dominate the scene.
The damp places of the world
remained their domain.
By the Jurassic,
when dinosaurs ruled the Earth,
amphibians looked more or less
the same as they do today.
If it ain't broke, don't fix it!
Today
there are around 7,000 species.
The smallest are just
a few millimetres long,
the biggest is the size of a human.
Under the cover of darkness,
the monster hunts.
It's nearly two metres long, giant,
but dwarfed by ancient relatives.
Fossils reveal
ancient amphibian cousins,
like Prionosuchus,
nine metres long.
A slow metabolism means it can go
for weeks without feeding,
but when it does hunt, it ambushes
fish and smaller amphibians...
using a vacuum to try
and draw them into its mouth.
This species has barely changed
for 160 million years.
But their cousins
have diversified with style.
Ninety percent of the world's
amphibians are frogs!
Their success is thanks
to the tools of their trade,
not least their iconic frog legs.
These are not just menu items,
but a masterful way of travelling
efficiently and dodging danger.
Before they leap, the frogs
stretch their muscles and tendons,
generating mechanical energy
that catapults them forwards.
Some are so good at it
that they seem to walk on water.
Frogs aren't the biggest creatures.
For them it's a dangerous world.
Wherever they roam,
they need to keep on hopping.
When they're not hopping to escape,
they can do it in pursuit of food,
utilising another frog-tastic tool.
A lightning-fast sticky tongue.
Like high speed Velcro,
it's thrown at the victim.
The fleshy end wraps around the
bug, coating it with sticky saliva.
Forget 'blink and you'll miss it'.
A frog could strike out five times
before your eyelids were open.
The biggest tongue
belongs to the bull frog.
It's a good fly swat ...
that can even be used
to catch birds.
Then its big eye balls
help shove it down its throat.
Though sometimes its eyes
are bigger than its stomach.
An emperor moth caterpillar.
It's binge-eating,
loading its body with nutrients,
ready to transform
into an adult moth.
A six centimetre
succulent sack of protein.
But for a European tree frog
there's a problem.
The bug is bigger than he is.
And it's covered
with irritating hairs.
Time to jump ship.
Generally, the ravenous bug-eating
appetites of amphibians
benefit others: they chow down on
pests, controlling their numbers.
But they don't discriminate,
and sometimes useful animals
also end up on the menu.
The world would be buried in poop
were it not for poop-eaters.
Dung beetles are tireless workers
who dedicate their lives
to cleaning up after others.
It's not enough
to win them respect.
They feed on dung and collect it
to lay their eggs in.
An edible nursery for their young.
In fact, dung gets them in the mood
as they begin
their family planning.
But it's hard to find privacy, away
from the prying eyes of a toad.
Amphibians can't chew their food,
hence their generous stomachs.
Their multi-functional mouths
are musical too.
When the tree frogs blow up
their balloons to impress a mate
they prefer to do it
under the safe cover of darkness.
Frogs have simple ears
that are well designed
to pick up the high frequency
love songs.
But others sometimes listen in.
Fire bellied toads,
so-called for the dazzling orange
blotches on their undersides
put-their-all
into their performance.
To sing they pump themselves
full of air
and shift it back and forth
through their vocal sacs.
It means they're very buoyant!
It's such an impressive display
that the odd frog gets lured in.
After some confused fumbling,
they get back to business.
But there's a downside
to his performance strategy.
Floaters are easy to spot
and vulnerable to attack.
The toads produce a venom that can
irritate the throats of anything
that tries to eat them,
but it doesn't always work.
The flood meadows
they use for their displays
are a favoured feeding ground
for migratory birds.
One male sees the intruder
and puts on a different show,
curling to show his orange patches,
a warning
that he won't taste nice.
And it seems to do the trick.
Each coupling
results in up to 300 eggs
and they too
will face a life of peril.
But frogs and toads have many
tricks to help them through.
The famous slimy skin of amphibians
is a winner.
They can breathe through it
in water.
But can cope on dry land.
It makes them weather-proof.
And can provide cryptic camo.
The skin makes its own slime from
mucous glands to keep is moist.
And in some species
the glands also produce poisons.
Along the ears of toads,
the glands contain a neurotoxin
called bufotoxin or frog toxin.
Many poisonous species
advertise their talent,
but few with the flare
of the fire salamander.
It might have misjudged the stream,
but there's no mistaking
the warning signs.
Black and yellow
indicate poison glands
that run head to tail
along both sides of his body.
This little salamander
is a creature of habit,
he likes to spend his time
travelling around
just 60 square meters
of damp forest that he calls home.
He has favoured hiding places that
he'll use regularly for decades.
And as he patrols, he's constantly
on the lookout for food.
An earthworm
is hard to get to grips with.
Amphibian kind don't chew their
food, it's straight down the hatch.
He can wander boldly
through the forest
thanks to his chemical defence.
He produces alkaloid toxins
that can cause muscle contractions
and hyperventilation
in other animals.
It also kills
fungal and bacterial infections,
keeping his skin
healthy and bright.
There are more than 650 salamanders
in the world.
All have toxins to keep away biting
insects and stop fungal infections,
but they're not all deadly.
Some of the biggest
come out at night.
It looks like the stuff
of nightmares,
but North America's hellbender
does not live up to its name.
It's a more primitive model,
with gill slits and no eyelids.
Lurking in the shadows, he hunts.
A more likeable cousin
is on the move.
One group of small salamanders
is known as the newts,
in this case the Sierra variety.
Every year they march back
to their place of birth,
ready to make more baby newts.
Most amphibians
are nervous out in the open,
but orange is a warning sign.
This species has toxins
100 times more potent than cyanide.
If a human ate one,
they'd drop dead.
Like all of amphibian kind,
they breed in water.
But at this pool party
anything goes.
Boys on boys, boys on girls.
Salamander sex
is as colourful as their skin.
But at least some get it right.
Twigs in the pond are decorated
with sticky sacks of eggs.
A European relative
is more reserved.
The best party hat is worn
by the great crested newt.
If a male can impress a female
with his outfit,
then she'll allow him to pass over
a package of sperm.
He'll drop it off
and she'll pick it up
and use it to fertilise her eggs.
The female folds a leaf
and lays an egg into the fold,
its jelly
cementing the two halves together.
It's a painstaking approach,
but it's the best she can do
to hide her babies
from hungry mouths.
Like all amphibians,
the babies need a makeover
before they'll be ready
to breed themselves.
It will take four months for them
to become smaller versions
of their parents.
Though they're salamanders,
these newts aren't very toxic,
but even their most deadly of kin
can't compete
with a South American cousin.
You might wonder what indigenous
hunters have to do with amphibians.
In the dense Amazon rainforest,
they're hunting squirrel monkeys.
They're using a blow gun,
with poison-tipped darts.
It kills within seconds.
And you've guessed it.
The poison comes from
the aptly named poison dart frogs,
tiny, colourful
rainforest inhabitants.
The frogs are only a few
centimetres long,
but don't underestimate
their potency.
Some species contain enough toxin
to kill half a dozen people.
Deadly as they are,
they're model parents.
The Red Amazonica couple
will be faithful to each other,
though it's dad
who does most of the parenting.
The female's contribution is
to lay a few unfertilised eggs
as food for her infants.
But after that
she leaves them too it.
Normally amphibians
lay eggs in water,
but these must survive
in a blob of jelly.
The male stands guard
until the eggs hatch,
and then he offers them a lift.
Instinctively,
a tadpole wriggles onto his back.
And then he begins an epic journey.
The rainforest has high humidity,
but large bodies of water are hard
to find and teeming with predators.
But he has a plan.
He clambers skywards
until he sees a bromeliad.
Bromeliads are not parasites,
but they grow on other plants
to get them closer to sunlight.
To live high up,
they have the useful habit
of collecting rain water.
It's to keep themselves wet,
but in the process providing
hot tubs for tadpoles.
Dad drops each baby
in its own plant pot,
an aquatic nursery
where it can live in safety
until it's ready to transform
into an adult frog and hop off.
It's hard-core parenting,
but there's another frog
that wins 'Father of the Year'.
Huge rivers and wetlands of Africa
are subject to seasonal drying out.
It leaves some residents
high and dry.
Thousands of matchbox-sized
tadpoles and their beefy dad.
He's on guard
and under submarine attack.
It's another marauding male.
And dad's not happy.
These heavy-weights,
football-sized frogs,
will fight to the death
over who gets to keep the babies.
Our devoted dad wins.
He'll fearlessly defend his brood
for three weeks
until their metamorphosis
is complete,
but a lot can change in that time.
The mercury is rising.
The young
are halfway to becoming chowder.
Dad must act fast.
Instinct tells him what to do.
He puts his powerful
hopping legs to work.
He's a dambuster.
The larger pool should keep them
going for a while.
Even with a hero in the family, the
hoppers face a life of hardship.
Few predators turn their nose up
at frog legs.
For the common frog of Europe, the
grass snake is enemy number one.
The water-loving reptile terrorises
all the amphibians
of its wetland home.
But it's important to look
before you leap.
Frogs certainly
make a popular dish.
Even bears aren't above a bit of
weight-lifting to sample the goods.
Damp rocky hideouts
equal a salamander buffet.
The bears
seem to instinctively know
which kinds are the least toxic
before they chow down.
There are dangers everywhere.
But this African red toad
thinks he's found a safe house.
But he's not the first
to shelter here.
A deadly spitting cobra.
It looks like toad in the hole,
but it's not over yet.
If all else fails, the toad
has another trick up his sleeve.
He inflates his body so much so
that even the hungry snake
can't get its mouth around him.
Amazing amphibians
use every trick in the book
to survive a dangerous world.
But poisons,
hopping and puffing are nothing.
Meet the masters of disguise.
Leaf-cutter ants work tirelessly
to gather vegetation
to take back to their nests,
building a food store.
And it's not surprising
that after putting so much work
into their larder,
they'll fiercely defend it.
Trespassers are not welcome.
And yet there's a frog inside.
Any other frog in here
would find itself under attack,
but not this one.
Ants recognise each other,
not by sight but by scent,
the chemical signals
they all give off.
The frog has developed
its own unique cologne, eau de ant.
In the cool damp basement of the
ant nest it can raise its young,
protected by the fearsome ants
like a member of the family.
But there are other creepy crawlies
you really don't want to mess with.
The tarantula
is an intimidating predator
that stalks the rainforest
for any small animals she can eat.
A spider cave protects her babies
until they're as scary
as their mother.
It's not a place
for the faint-hearted.
A frog has found its way
into her lair.
But he survives. Again,
his pheromones reassure the spider.
He's a welcome lodger,
some reports even suggest
a spider keeps a frog as a pet,
though in fact
it's a mutual arrangement.
Big scary spider
protects her little frog,
and the amphibian pays its rent
by eating ants
and other predatory insects that
might harm her baby spiderlings.
It appears that amphibians
have found ingenious solutions
to almost any obstacle,
and as a result,
their kingdom knows no bounds.
Humid tropical rainforest
looks like frog-heaven,
but not here atop a mountain.
But melting glaciers form pools
and potential
for one intrepid amphibian.
The Siberian salamander can cope
with minus 45 degrees centigrade.
They've even be known
to survive the odd winter,
frozen solid in permafrost.
But the weirdest of them all
lives inside the mountain itself.
In limestone karsts under the Alps
lurks Europe's only
cave-dwelling vertebrate.
Legend records it as a baby dragon,
living in the caves,
slowly growing
into a fearsome beast.
The strangest of specialists,
the olm.
It only reaches
30 centimetres long.
Like most young amphibians,
it has feathery external gills,
but they stay with it
throughout life.
It's blind and finds its food
with hearing and smell.
Some local people
call it the human fish
because of its ghostly
pigmentless skin.
Living underground in perpetual
darkness it has no need for colour.
Amazing amphibians
have certainly conquered the globe.
But the world still throws
challenges at them.
When winter arrives
in northern forests,
waterways are brought
to a standstill, the ground freezes
and so do the bodies
of any animals trapped within.
It's good for nature.
Germs and bacteria will be killed,
seeds will be protected
until they grow in spring,
but for many individuals
this is the end of the road.
But amphibians
have one last magic trick
and it's one
of biblical proportions.
Spring sunshine
slowly unlocks the forest
from months in suspended animation.
Under the leaf-litter,
the iced-up body of a frog.
Even his eyes
are solid balls of ice.
But as the ice melts
the dead seem to rise again.
First his heart
begins to gently beat,
attempting to kick-start
his circulation.
Blood reaches his brain.
It's like the on-switch.
His liver
produced an oily antifreeze
which was pumped around his body.
So although the water in his body
froze, his cells did not.
They just had to wait for the thaw.
A big of wriggling to warm up,
and he's ready to hop.
Frogs can shut down
for eight months of the year,
but it doesn't damage
their zest for life.
And to make the most
of a fleeting northern spring,
there's work to be done.
Amphibians
are almost irrepressible.
They've hopped and croaked through
hundreds of millions of years
of harsh weather
and hungry predators.
Now there's a new threat,
chytridiomycosis,
a virus spread by fungi that kills
frogs by stopping their ability
to control their body salts
and moisture levels.
It's already wiped out 200 species.
It's an endless struggle onwards.
But the world over, scientists are
trying to find a way to help.
They won't allow the frog family
to croak its last.
And coupled with the frogs'
enthusiasm for breeding,
there's every chance
they can bounce back.